Guide to the Maureen Owen Collection of Greenwich Village Poetry
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Maureen Owen collection of Greenwich Village poetry
1975-1981
YCAL MSS 218
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.5
(3 boxes)
Collection consists of audio recordings, originally recorded on reel-to-reel tape and audio cassette. Many of the recordings are of poets reading their work or the work of others at literary events held by the Poetry Project at St. Mark's Church-in-the-Bowery in New York City. Also includes recordings of poets reading their work and being interviewed on Susan Howe's radio shows on WBAI Radio in New York. Miscellaneous readings recorded in Connecticut and elsewhere are present. The collection includes audio publications Black Box No. 12 and BREATHINGSPACE/77. The recordings include readings by the following authors: Russell Banks, Regina Beck, Ted Berrigan, Elizabeth Bishop, Ed Friedman, John Godfrey, Ted Greenwald, Barbara Guest, John Francis Alexander Heath-Stubbs, Dale Herd, Bob Holman, Fanny Howe, Carole Spearin McCauley, Douglas Messerli, Eileen Myles, Charles North, George Oppen, Maureen Owen, Ron Padgett, Charles Rezkinoff, Adrienne Rich, Ed Sanders, Ron Silliman, Jack Spicer, and Virgil Thomson.
Other Storage Formats: Audio Recordings
Owen, Maureen, 1943-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Richard Deming, 2004.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Digitized audio files are available via this finding aid for streaming on-site at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library. Digital versions of the original recordings are available for reference use to scholars off-site. Original recordings are housed in Restricted Fragile in boxes 1-3, and may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator.
MAUREEN OWEN (1943- )
Maureen Owen, poet, editor, publisher, and editor, was born in 1943 in Graceville, Minnesota. Owen began publishing and editing Telephone Books and Telephone magazine in 1969. During the 1970s, she worked as coordinator and director (1976-1980) of the Poetry Project at St. Mark's Church-in-the-Bowery in New York City. She taught writing and magazine production workshops for the Poetry Project, a Greenwich Village collective founded in 1966 as a forum for public literary events and as a resource center for writers.
Owen's publications include Country Rush (1973), No Travels Journal (1975), Hearts in Space (1980), AE (Amelia Earhart) (1984), Zombie Notes (1986), Imaginary Income (1992), Untapped Maps (1993) and American Rush (1998).
Owen received a National Endowment for the Arts fellowship grant in 1979-80, and in 1998 was awarded by the Foundation of Contemporary Performance Arts. She received the Los Angeles Times Book Festival Prize in 1999. Owen has taught at Edinboro University, Swarthmore College, Saint Joseph College (CT), and Naropa University.
Scope and Contents
The Maureen Owen Collection of Greenwich Village Poetry consists of audio recordings on reel-to-reel tape and audio cassette. Many of the recordings are of poets reading their work or the work of others at literary events held by the Poetry Project at St. Mark's Church-in-the-Bowery in New York City. There are also recordings of poets reading their work and being interviewed on Susan Howe's radio shows on WBAI Radio in New York. Miscellaneous readings recorded in Connecticut and elsewhere are present as well. The collection includes two audio publications which were originally issued on cassette, Black Box No. 12 and BREATHINGSPACE/77.
The recordings include readings by the following authors: Russell Banks, Regina Beck, Ted Berrigan, Elizabeth Bishop, Ed Friedman, John Godfrey, Ted Greenwald, Barbara Guest, John Francis Alexander Heath-Stubbs, Dale Herd, Bob Holman, Fanny Howe, Carole Spearin McCauley, Douglas Messerli, Eileen Myles, Charles North, George Oppen, Maureen Owen, Ron Padgett, Charles Rezkinoff, Adrienne Rich, Ed Sanders, Ron Silliman, Jack Spicer, and Virgil Tomson.
American poetry -- 20th Century; Oral interpretation of poetry; Poets, American -- 20th Century; Greenwich Village (New York, N.Y.) -- Poetry; Audiovisual materials; Sound recordings; Literary readings; Poets -- 20th Century; Black box; Breathingspace; Adam, Helen, 1909-1993; Banks, Russell, 1940-; Beck, Regina; Berrigan, Ted, 1934-1983; Bishop, Elizabeth, 1911-1979; Friedman, Ed, 1950-; Godfrey, John, 1945-; Greenwald, Ted, 1942-; Guest, Barbara, 1920-2006; Heath-Stubbs, John, 1918-2006; Herd, Dale, 1940-; Holman, Bob, 1948-; Howe, Fanny, 1940-; Howe, Susan, 1937-; McCauley, Carole Spearin; Messerli, Douglas, 1947-; Myles, Eileen, 1949-; North, Charles, 1941-; Oppen, George, 1908-1984; Owen, Maureen, 1943-; Padgett, Ron, 1942-; Reznikoff, Charles, 1894-1976; Rich, Adrienne, 1929-2012; Sanders, Ed, 1939-; Silliman, Ronald, 1946-; Spicer, Jack; Thomson, Virgil, 1896-1989; St. Mark's Church in-the-Bowery (New York, N.Y.); WBAI Radio (New York, N.Y.)
- Audio Recordings, 1975-1981; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Recordings, is organized into four subseries: St. Mark's In-the-Bowery Poetry Project Readings, WBAI Radio (New York, N.Y.) Programs, Audio Publications, and Other Recordings. Each subseries has been arranged chronologically. The original format of the recording is identified in brackets following the folder title. In some cases, readings on different dates were recorded onto a single source; a note references the other readings that were found on the original recording. Original recordings which were transferred to multiple compact discs are noted in the finding aid by discrete audio files. Tracks for single recordings have also been separated where indicated by individual audio files. Undated recordings are arranged at the end of each subseries. Original recordings are in Restricted Fragile.
  - ST. MARK'S CHURCH IN-THE-BOWERY POETRY PROJECT READINGS
    - Sanders, Ed. Workshop on Investigative poetry [Reel to reel], 1977 Oct 20 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
      Originally recorded on single reel
      Q&A session at end of second disc
      Total running time: 92.94 min
    - Holman, Bob [Reel to reel], 1978 Oct (Box 1, Folder 3)
      With introduction and Poetry Project announcements
      Recording has dropouts of sound
      Originally recorded as track 1 on reel shared with 1978 Oct Helen Adam reading
      Running time: 46.31 min
    - Adam, Helen [Reel to reel], 1978 Oct (Box 1, Folder 4)
      With introduction
      Originally recorded as track 2 on reel shared with 1978 Oct Bob Holman reading
      Running time: 47.50 min
    - Guest, Barbara [Reel to reel], 1978 Dec 13 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Includes Poetry Project announcements and introduction
      Originally recorded on side 1, track 1 of reel shared with 1978 Dec 13 Charles North reading
      Running time: 36.18 min
    - North, Charles [Reel to reel], 1978 Dec 13 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Track 2 includes introduction and ends at 33.46
      Originally recorded on side 1, track 4 of reel shared with 1978 Dec 13 Barbara Guest reading
      Running time: 33.43 min
    - Howe, Fanny [Reel to reel], 1978 Dec 17 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Originally recorded on left track of reel shared with 1978 Dec 17 reading by Maureen Owen
      Running time: 21.24 min
    - Owen, Maureen [Reel to reel], 1978 Dec 17 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Originally recorded on right track of reel shared with 1978 Dec 17 reading by Fanny Howe
      Running time: 26.50 min
    - Greenwald, Ted [Reel to reel], 1979 Feb 28 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Originally recorded as track 1 on reel shared with 1979 Feb 28 Russell Banks reading
      Running time: 44.00 min
    - Banks, Russell [Reel to reel], 1979 Feb 28 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Originally recorded as tracks 2 and 3 on reel shared with 1979 Feb 28 Ted Greenwald reading
      Running time: 47.41 min
    - Godfrey, John [Reel to reel], 1979 Mar 7 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Originally recorded as side 1 of reel shared with 1979 Mar 7 Dale Herd reading
      Running time: 41.30 min
    - Herd, Dale [Reel to reel], 1979 Mar 7 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Originally recorded on two tracks on side 2 of reel shared with 1979 Mar 7 John Godfrey reading
      Running time: 55.58 min
    - Celebration of Emily Dickinson's birthday [Reel to reel], 1979 Dec 10 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
      Disc one includes introduction and schedule information. Readers: Jan Heller Levi, Charles Bernstein, Susan Lightus, Charles Doria, Virginia Terrace, Barbara Guest, Madeleine Keller, Vicky Hudspith, Armand Schwerner, Karen Edwards, and Jackson Mac Low
      Disc two includes introduction. Readers: Maureen Owen, Susan Howe, Jay Leyda. Q&A session follows
      Total running time: 97 min
    - Bloomsday Readings Series [Reel to reel], 1980 Feb 24 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Wachtel, Chuck. Reading from "Joe the Engineer". Starts 0.00
      Holman, Bob. Reading Panic DJ, Tear to Open, and new poems. Starts 30.36
      Owen, Maureen. Starts 52.20
      Total running time: 79.30 min
    - Myles, Eileen [Cassette], 1981 Oct (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Recording is overdubbed until 6.40
      Running time is 39.01 min
    - Friedman, Ed. Reading from "Journals from the Table, Poetry from the Podium" [Cassette], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
      Includes reading by Barret Watten on second disc
      Running time: 90.04 min
  - WBAI RADIO (NEW YORK, N.Y.) PROGRAMS
    - Susan Howe's Radio Shows & Interviews
      - Reznikoff, Charles [Reel to reel], [1975?] (Box 1, Folder 19)
        2 tracks, total running time: 60.69 min
      - Bishop, Elizabeth [Reel to reel], 1977 Apr (Box 1, Folder 20)
        2 tracks, total running time: 68.46 min
      - Heath-Stubbs, John Francis Alexander [Reel to reel], 1978 Nov 29 (Box 2, Folder 21)
        Tracks are different versions of same recording
        Tracks include unidentified western music
        2 tracks, running time: 54.48 min
      - Myles, Eileen [Reel to reel], 1978 Dec (Box 2, Folder 22)
        Track includes music by The Ramones
        Running time: 30.26 min
      - Oppen, George [Reel to reel], 1979 Apr 25, 29 (Box 2, Folder 23)
        Original container notes copy of recording transferred 1981 Jun 15
        2 tracks, total running time: 46.51 min
      - Rich, Adrienne. Interview and reading [Reel to reel], [1980?] (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
        Total running time: 92.33 min
      - Beck, Regina [Reel to reel], n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26)
        Running time: 23.55 min
  - AUDIO PUBLICATIONS
    - Black Box No. 12 [Cassette], 1977 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      Only partial transfer of original recording due to condition of audio tape
      _Works by Audre Lord, Allen Ginsberg, Leon Damas, Cynthia Genser, Tess Gallagher, Henry Rasof, Lynn Sukenick, Charles Bernstein, Beth Joselow, Joanna Cattonar
      Running time: 22.36
    - Wellman, John, ed. BREATHINGSPACE/77. [Cassette], [1978] (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
      Works by Beth Anderson, Richard Kostelanetz, Philip Corner, Bruce Andrews, George Quasha & Charles Stein, Charles Morrow, Tom Johnson, Annea Lockwood, John Cage, Bliem Kern, Henry Rasof, John Wellman & Annamarie Prins, Jackson Maclow
      Running time: 143 min
  - OTHER RECORDINGS
    - Thomson, Virgil. "The Art Song in America" [Reel to reel], 1979 Apr 12 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      Incomplete recording
      Running time: 47.55 min
    - Berrigan, Ted. Poetry reading at SCCC, New Haven, CT. [Reel to reel], 1979 Nov 20 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      Originally recorded as track 1, side 1 of reel with 1979 Nov 20 reading by Ron Padgett
      Running time: 33.55 min
    - Padgett, Ron. Poetry reading [Reel to reel], 1979 Nov 20 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      Originally recorded as track 1, side 2 of reel with 1979 Nov 20 reading by Ted Berrigan
      Running time: 23.02 min
    - Messerli, Douglas. Residencies for Writers Workshop [Cassette], 1980 May 8 (Box 2, Folder 33-35)
      Total running time: 156.19 min
    - Reading in Hartford, CT. Readers: Carole Spearin McCauley and Maureen Owen [Reel to reel], n.y. Jun 3 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      Incomplete recording. Level drops
      Running time: 48.18 min
    - Callahan, Bob. Recording about Jaime De Angulo - "Old Time Stories" [Cassette], n.d. (Box 2, Folder 37)
      Running time: 30.44 min
    - Silliman, Ron. Residencies for Writers Workshop [Cassette], n.d. (Box 2, Folder 38-40)
      Running time: 171.04 min
    - Spicer, Jack. Reading "Billy the Kid" and "The Holy Grail: the Book of the Death of Arthur" with lecture [Reel to reel] (Box 2, Folder 41)
      Running time: 21.44 min
- RESTRICTED FRAGILE, 1; (2 boxes)
  Restricted Fragile contains fragile orginal recordings which may be seen only with the permission of the curator. Digital reference copies are available.
  - Folders 1-2 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Folders 3-4 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Folders 5-6 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Folders 7-8 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Folders 9-10 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Folders 11-12 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Folders 13-14 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Folder 15 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Folder 16 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Folders 17-18 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Folder 19 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Folder 20 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Folder 21 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Folder 22 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Folder 23 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Folders 24-25 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Folder 26 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Folder 27 (Box 2, Folder 59-61)
  - Folder 28-29 (Box 2, Folder 62-64)
  - Folder 30 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Folders 31-32 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Folders 33-35 (Box 3, Folder 67-68)
  - Folder 36 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Folder 37 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Folders 38-40 (Box 3, Folder 71-73)
  - Folder 41 (Box 3, Folder 74)